Communism, Socialism, and Left-Wing Politics Collection, 1891-1998
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Communism, socialism, and radical left politics collection
1891-1998
MS 452
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Includes printed materials, correspondence, journals and organizational records documenting women's involvement in socialist and communist movements in the United States, United Kingdom, and internationally. Individuals represented include Ella Reeve Bloor, Adeline Champney, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Dolores (Pasionaria) Ibarruri, Zelda Kahan, Rosa Luxembourg, Betty Millard, Kate Richards O'Hare, Anna Louise Strong, and Clara Zetkin.
The Communism, Socialism, and Left-Wing Politics Collection consists of printed material documenting women's involvement in socialist and communist movements in the United States, United Kingdom, and internationally. It is divided into two series: BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS and PRINTED MATERIALS. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS includes pamphlets by and about communist and socialist women: Ella Reeve Bloor, Adeline Champney, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Dolores (Pasionaria) Ibarruri, Zelda Kahan, Rosa Luxembourg, Betty Millard, Kate Richards O'Hare, Anna Louise Strong, and Clara Zetkin. There is also a photograph of Elizabeth Gurley Flynn. The PRINTED MATERIALS contain newspaper clippings including those about the U.S. Communist Party's newspaper the Daily Worker, miscellaneous pamphlets, and printed material on Communism in the United States and Great Britain. These reflect both pro- and anti-communist perspectives. There are also pamphlets about the Palmer raids as well as several published by the Fabian Society in Great Britain.
This collection is organized into two series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. PRINTED MATERIALS
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this finding aid.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Bloor, Ella Reeve, 1862-1951; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Ibárruri, Dolores, 1895-; Luxemburg, Rosa, 1871-1919; Millard, Betty; Strong, Anna Louise, 1885-1970; O'Hare, Kate Richards, 1877-1948; Communist Party of the United States of America--History--Sources; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities--History--Sources; Communists--Biography--Sources; Communist Party of the United States of America--History--Sources; Socialism--History--Sources; Women and communism--History--Sources; Women communists--Biography--Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Bloor, Ella Reeve, 1935-79 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Champney, Adeline, 1903-04, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley, 1940-64, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ibárruri, Dolores (Pasionaria), 1938, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kahan, Zelda, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Luxembourg, Rosa, 1937, 1971-74, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Millard, Betty, 1948-98 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - O'Hare, Kate Richards, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Strong, Anna Louise, 1941, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Zetkin, Clara: pamphlets, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- SERIES II. PRINTED MATERIALS
  - Clippings and articles (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-79, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Daily Worker, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pamphlets (Box 1)
    - Fabian Women's Group, 1910-68 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Since the Buford Sailed" (Palmer Raids), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1891-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-5)